<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Brandon Castellano</title>
    <link>https://www.bcastell.com/categories/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Brandon Castellano</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 12:57:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.bcastell.com/categories/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Triclysm</title>
      <link>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/triclysm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 12:57:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/triclysm/</guid>
      <description>Triclysm Project Overview See the Triclysm project on Github at the following URL: https://github.com/Triclysm
Triclysm Previewer Triclysm Previewer (link) is a cross-platform application for developing, previewing, and streaming (via Ethernet or Wi-Fi) to a physical LED cube/voxel-based display. Cross-platform, written in C++, using SDL/OpenGL as a back-end, with Lua as the primary scripting language for animations.
In the future, a rewrite is planned, utilizing Python for a majority of the code, and allowing it to be used for animation development as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DVR-Scan</title>
      <link>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/dvr-scan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/dvr-scan/</guid>
      <description>DVR-Scan  Overview DVR-Scan is a command-line application for detecting areas in a video that contain motion, automatically extracting each motion segment as a separate file for further viewing or processing. This makes managing a large amount of footage from, for example, security cameras/DVRs, a much more manageable task, as only the areas of interest need to be reviewed after processing with DVR-Scan.
See DVR-Scan on Readthedocs for more information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PySceneDetect</title>
      <link>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/pyscenedetect/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/pyscenedetect/</guid>
      <description>PySceneDetect Overview PySceneDetect is a command-line application and a Python library for detecting scene changes in videos, automatically splitting the video into separate clips. Not only is it free and open-source software (FOSS), but there are several detection methods available (see Features), from simple threshold-based fade in/out detection, to advanced content aware fast-cut detection.
Download Click here to download the latest release of PySceneDetect. Note that PySceneDetect is cross-platform, and is supported for Windows, Linux, and OSX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biopsy Bot</title>
      <link>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/biopsybot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bcastell.com/projects/biopsybot/</guid>
      <description>General Overview A remote-control robot capable of gathering a biological sample in unknown areas, Biopsy Bot was developed as a final project for the 4th year Mechatronic System Design course offered at UWO. The purpose of the project was to develop a robot capable of remotely navigating (with the aid of an on-board wireless camera) an area of unknown, rocky terrain, in order to gather and return a biological sample from a mysterious blob (made of Jello).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>